<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Koushik Krishnan</title>
    <description>Write an awesome description for your new site here. You can edit this line in _config.yml. It will appear in your document head meta (for Google search results) and in your feed.xml site description.
</description>
    <link>http://koek67.github.io/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://koek67.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2014 01:38:56 -0500</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2014 01:38:56 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Microwave Welder</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This weekend my friend and I decided to convert an old microwave into a spot welder. We were inspired
by a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vrlvqib94xQ&quot;&gt;video&lt;/a&gt; on YouTube on how to do it so we spent a
weekend trying to make it a reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;you-will-need&quot;&gt;You will need:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An old microwave to take apart (or a brand new one that you dont really care about)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;About 4 feet of the thickest wire you can find/afford at a hardware store (Note: the thicker the better)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work gloves with NO HOLES IN THEM&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Non synthetic clothing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Something that can reliably cut metal. This can be a hacksaw, plasma cutter, or in our case a reciprocating saw with the right type of blade.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A bench vice or a handful of c-clamps&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Basic tools such as screwdrivers to take apart the microwave with&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-0&quot;&gt;Step 0&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take apart the microwave. Inside you’ll find lots of cool, awesome high voltage parts but the
one we are most interested in is the transformer which will look something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.o-digital.com/uploads/2179/2225-1/Microwave_Oven_Transformer_HVT_700_367.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;transformer&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remove this part from the microwave. Make sure to wear your gloves while doing this and make sure that the
microwave is unplugged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-1&quot;&gt;Step 1&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that your transformer is out, it’s time to learn a little bit about how these things work. Transformers are
essentially devices that change the amount of current and voltage from a given source to fit the needs of a certain
appliance. Normally, a microwave will take the current from the wall outlet and increase the voltage to 20,000 volts.
For our purposes, we will instead modify the transformer to increase instead the amperage up to 2,000 A.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How does this melt metal? This happens because of the difference in resistance between the copper wire and the iron/steel
piece of metal. Normally this delta is negligible but with  a current this high, the difference is enough to cause the steel
piece to melt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-2&quot;&gt;Step 2&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, you need to cut open the transformer and replace the secondary coil of it with one single winding of the thick wire you
have. This wil reduce the voltage of the output and increase the current greatly. In order to cut open the transformer I suggest
placing it in a vice and cutting along the welded seem on the transformer. This seem is pretty thin so a simple hacksaw should be fine
but because I am lazy I used a reciprocating saw with a hacksaw blade. Be careful with this step and make sure not to not damage the
primary coil (the coil with the thicker wire originally).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-3&quot;&gt;Step 3&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plug it in and melt stuff!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay not really but you are basically done at this point. Remember to be mindful of danger in this project. Make sure to wear safety
goggles and non-synthetic clothes. Here are some pictures and a video of my final product. It doesn’t look nearly as good as the one
in the YouTube video I followed but it works. Have fun and be safe!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-final-product&quot;&gt;The Final Product&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.dropbox.com/s/sg2gu9j7hz5uikz/welder.jpg?dl=1&quot; alt=&quot;transformer&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.dropbox.com/s/0lofhl35b2smqcj/welder2.jpg?dl=1&quot; alt=&quot;transformer&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;//player.vimeo.com/video/112283913&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; height=&quot;500&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 12 Apr 2014 13:21:14 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://koek67.github.io/projects/2014/04/12/microwave-welder.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://koek67.github.io/projects/2014/04/12/microwave-welder.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>projects</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
