<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Koushik Krishnan</title>
    <description>Welcome to Koushik Krishnan&#39;s page! A simple site to showcase all the random things I do in my free time. It&#39;s always nice to look back on these endeavors and who knows, maybe all of this will be helpful to someone someday. Take care!</description>
    <link>http://koek67.github.io/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://koek67.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2014 00:55:34 -0500</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2014 00:55:34 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Microwave Welder</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This weekend my friend and I decided to convert an old microwave into a spot welder. We were inspired
by a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vrlvqib94xQ&quot;&gt;video&lt;/a&gt; on YouTube on how to do it so we spent a
weekend trying to make it a reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;you-will-need&quot;&gt;You will need:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An old microwave to take apart (or a brand new one that you dont really care about)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;About 4 feet of the thickest wire you can find/afford at a hardware store (Note: the thicker the better)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work gloves with NO HOLES IN THEM&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Non synthetic clothing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Something that can reliably cut metal. This can be a hacksaw, plasma cutter, or in our case a reciprocating saw with the right type of blade.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A bench vice or a handful of c-clamps&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Basic tools such as screwdrivers to take apart the microwave with&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-0&quot;&gt;Step 0&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take apart the microwave. Inside you’ll find lots of cool, awesome high voltage parts but the
one we are most interested in is the transformer which will look something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.o-digital.com/uploads/2179/2225-1/Microwave_Oven_Transformer_HVT_700_367.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;transformer&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remove this part from the microwave. Make sure to wear your gloves while doing this and make sure that the
microwave is unplugged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-1&quot;&gt;Step 1&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that your transformer is out, it’s time to learn a little bit about how these things work. Transformers are
essentially devices that change the amount of current and voltage from a given source to fit the needs of a certain
appliance. Normally, a microwave will take the current from the wall outlet and increase the voltage to 20,000 volts.
For our purposes, we will instead modify the transformer to increase instead the amperage up to 2,000 A.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How does this melt metal? This happens because of the difference in resistance between the copper wire and the iron/steel
piece of metal. Normally this delta is negligible but with  a current this high, the difference is enough to cause the steel
piece to melt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-2&quot;&gt;Step 2&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, you need to cut open the transformer and replace the secondary coil of it with one single winding of the thick wire you
have. This wil reduce the voltage of the output and increase the current greatly. In order to cut open the transformer I suggest
placing it in a vice and cutting along the welded seem on the transformer. This seem is pretty thin so a simple hacksaw should be fine
but because I am lazy I used a reciprocating saw with a hacksaw blade. Be careful with this step and make sure not to not damage the
primary coil (the coil with the thicker wire originally).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-3&quot;&gt;Step 3&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plug it in and melt stuff!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay not really but you are basically done at this point. Remember to be mindful of danger in this project. Make sure to wear safety
goggles and non-synthetic clothes. Here are some pictures and a video of my final product. It doesn’t look nearly as good as the one
in the YouTube video I followed but it works. Have fun and be safe!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-final-product&quot;&gt;The Final Product&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.dropbox.com/s/sg2gu9j7hz5uikz/welder.jpg?dl=1&quot; alt=&quot;transformer&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.dropbox.com/s/0lofhl35b2smqcj/welder2.jpg?dl=1&quot; alt=&quot;transformer&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;//player.vimeo.com/video/112283913&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; height=&quot;500&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 12 Apr 2014 13:21:14 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://koek67.github.io/projects/2014/04/12/microwave-welder.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://koek67.github.io/projects/2014/04/12/microwave-welder.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>projects</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Benford&#39;s Law Simulation</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Github: &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/koek67/benfords-law-viewer&quot;&gt;Benford’s Law Viewer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, one of the biggest advantages that computer science gives me is the ability to test out peculiar mathematical
paradoxes and theorems in code and see them work in action, rather than just in a proof. One of the ways I found this useful
was when I decided to test Benford’s Law. I was inspired to do this after watching the Numberphile
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XXjlR2OK1kM&quot;&gt;video&lt;/a&gt; on the topic. The theory seemed a bit hard to believe so I decided to see
if I could replicate its results in code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-bit-of-background&quot;&gt;A Bit of Background&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what is Benford’s Law? It’s a mathematical principle that says that if you take the numbers you find in the real world, this
could mean numbers from stock prices, sports scores, report cards etc., that the probability that the leading digit will be 1 is
about 30%. Normally one might think that the probability should be 11% assuming that each number has an equal probability of being
a leading digit. To be more specific, the distribution of the probabilities looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.dropbox.com/s/yllv44j5hqc6aeo/benford3.jpg?dl=1&quot; alt=&quot;Benford&#39;s Law&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In essence what Benford’s Law is saying is that if you obtain a large set of numbers curated from your environment, a seemingly random
set of data, 30% of those numbers will have 1 as their leading digit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-does-this-happen&quot;&gt;Why does this happen?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason for this is that numbers in the real world are not totally random. For exmaple lets imagine that all numbers
in the world were between 1 and 1000. Using a random number generator its easy to say that the probability of getting one
number is about the same as getting another. But let’s look at this as if this were the prices of objects. If an object costs
$100, it would require a 100% increase to have a leading digit of 2. This would mean that something in the environment must cause this
object’s price to double, an event that is relatively unlikely. But let’s assume that this happens and the object now costs
$200. In order for it to have a leading digit of 3, it would require a 50% increase. As you can see, it is easier for the price of this object to leave the leading digit of 2 and move to a leading digit of 3 than it is to move from a 1 to a 2. Here is a table to better explain this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Leading Digit Transition&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Percentage Change Required&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1 -&amp;gt; 2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;100%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2 -&amp;gt; 3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;50%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3 -&amp;gt; 4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;33.33%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4 -&amp;gt; 5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;25%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;5 -&amp;gt; 6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;20%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;6 -&amp;gt; 7&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;16.66%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7 -&amp;gt; 8&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;14.3%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8 -&amp;gt; 9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;12.5%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9 -&amp;gt; 1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;11.1%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the transition from 1 -&amp;gt; 2 requires the greatest percentage increase, it makes sense that numbers in the real word tend
to stay in the range where the leading digit is 1 because it is the hardest to escape this region. In addition, since the required percentage increase decreases for every
subsequent transition, it means that it becomes increasingly easier to return back to a leading digit of one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-program&quot;&gt;The Program&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The program I wrote to simulate this was written in Java using good ol’ Swing graphics (function over form, my friends).
The issue I had to figure out was how to recreate “real world” numbers. While generating random numbers was easy, how could I
generate numbers that model those found around us. The solution I found for this was to generate random numbers with random
ranges. In code, it would look like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;
Random numGen = new Random();
numGen.nextInt(numGen.nextInt(numGen.nextInt(1000000)));
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My program can simulate a standard set of random numbers as well as random numbers with random ranges. In addition, I added a
box where a user can enter a set of numbers separated by spaces and view the distribution of leading digits in the set. I tried
this out with world population data, stock prices I found on Yahoo Finance and to my surprise both data sets matched Benford’s Law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All my code is on github (link is above) and the runnable jar is inside the repository for you to play around with. Have fun!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.dropbox.com/s/674wtht2ugwa8af/Screenshot%202014-11-27%2007.27.38.png?dl=1&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jun 2013 13:21:14 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://koek67.github.io/projects/2013/06/02/benfords-law-simulation.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://koek67.github.io/projects/2013/06/02/benfords-law-simulation.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>projects</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
